<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<doc>
	<url auto="true" type="str" verify="true"><![CDATA[https://www.nationalgeographic.com/animals/article/badger-culls-are-dividing-englands-rural-communities
]]></url>
	<categories theme="animals" auto="true" type="list" verify="true"/>
	<author auto="true" type="str" verify="true"><![CDATA[SIMON WORRALL]]></author>
	<title auto="true" type="str" verify="true"><![CDATA[Badger culls are dividing England’s rural communities]]></title>
	<publish_date auto="true" type="str" verify="true"><![CDATA[FEBRUARY 8, 2022]]></publish_date>
	<reading_time auto="true" type="str" verify="true"><![CDATA[• 20 MIN READ]]></reading_time>
	<editor_notes auto="true" type="str" verify="true"><![CDATA[Wildlife Watch is an investigative reporting project between National Geographic Society and National Geographic Partners focusing on wildlife crime and exploitation. Read more Wildlife Watch stories here, and learn more about National Geographic Society’s nonprofit mission at natgeo.com/impact. Send tips, feedback, and story ideas to NGP.WildlifeWatch@natgeo.com.]]></editor_notes>
	<text auto="true" type="str" verify="true"><![CDATA[PORTBURY, ENGLANDIt’s a clear October night near the village of Portbury, in Somerset, a county in western England. “We use this to monitor the badgers at night,” says my guide, an animal rights activist who asked me not to name her for her protection, as she hands me her thermal imaging scope. I train it on an ink-black line of trees and make out a few white dots. She asks for the device. They’re rabbits, she says.
As we follow a footpath alongside arable fields, she freezes: “Ooh!” she exclaims. “A badger!”
Sure enough, at the edge of the trees, I make out a shape with an arched back and long snout.
“Is it your first badger?” she asks. “Are you excited?”
Yes and yes.
The badger is Britain’s largest surviving terrestrial carnivore, after all other major predators, from wolves to lynx, have become extinct here. Residents since the end of the Ice Age, badgers are a keystone species whose presence helps keeps other animals—notably foxes, rats, mice—in balance. Their distinctive black-and-white face markings and comical gait, combined with their depiction in children’s classics, from the Beatrix Potter books to Kenneth Graham’s Wind in the Willows, have made them one of Britain’s most cherished creatures.
Beguiling and beloved as badgers are to many people, these nocturnal animals are also at the center of an inflamed debate: cattle farmers on one side, badger proponents on the other. The controversy hinges on bovine tuberculosis, a highly contagious disease that results in the slaughter of 30,000 infected cows in the U.K. each year.
Badgers share fields with cows and can spread bovine TB. That’s why the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (DEFRA) commissions licensed companies to shoot or trap thousands of badgers every year. The policy has strong support from farmers.
Badger activists dispute the efficacy of the culls and regard them as cruel and barbaric. Determinedly, they patrol cull areas to keep badgers from being killed (it’s illegal to shoot the animals when people are in the vicinity), risking harassment, even slashed tires, for their efforts. Anti-cull organizations post the details of cull company employees online and mount noisy demonstrations outside their homes, sometimes splashing blood on properties.
Each side can point to a raft of scientific data and statistics to justify its position for or against culling badgers, but the science remains contested and open to interpretation. Neither side accepts the other’s point of view. The result is a kind of ideological trench warfare, with the interests of cows or badgers pitted against each other.
“Cows are the major transmitters, not badgers,” says the activist I’m with in Somerset. She’d invited me to join her on a nighttime foray to safeguard badger setts—dens where multiple badger families live—by deterring shooters. Bovine TB, she insists, afflicts cattle because of “poor biosecurity” on farms—including the spreading of a contaminated mixture of manure and water on fields as fertilizer, missed targets for the removal of infected cattle, and poor disinfection of farms and vehicles. To prove her point, she refers to a 2013 study by Imperial College, London, that says badgers account for just 5.7 percent of direct TB transmission to cattle, though the study also found that culling can decrease infections by 16 percent.
“But it’s not about science,” she says. “It’s like in medieval times, when they tried pigs for spreading disease.”
“We know from various studies that controlling the disease in badgers, which [are] the main host in the wild, has positive impacts on the disease in cattle,” asserts Christine Middlemiss, the Scottish-born chief veterinary officer for the U.K. and DEFRA’s spokesperson. “Where we’ve used culls in high-risk areas, the level of disease is much reduced,” she says, adding that “we also know from genome sequencing that there is more badger spread to cattle than there is cattle spread to badgers.”
The National Farmers Union strongly supports DEFRA’s position. And a number of scientists affirm it. “You get a significant decrease in the rates of disease in cattle by killing badgers,” says James Wood, a veterinary epidemiologist at Cambridge University, citing the Randomised Badger Control Trial.
This study to determine the effectiveness of culling in curbing bovine TB ran from 1998 to 2007 and involved exterminating some 13,000 badgers. Analysis of the data ultimately suggested that over almost 10 years, with culls every year the first five years, the incidence of infections in cull areas could drop by as much as 16 percent.
Lord John Krebs, one of the chief architects of the trial, later said that culling badgers wouldn’t be a good way to control bovine TB because the costs would far outweigh the benefits.
Nonetheless, after the election in 2010 of a Conservative-led coalition government keen to accommodate its rural base, the advice of the researchers and Krebs was ignored, and plans were ramped up for the annual culling of badgers. The program began in 2013 and continues today.
Because badgers are active at night and are difficult to count, it’s not known exactly how many there are, but a 2017 study put the population in England and Wales at 485,000. In the years since the culls began, an estimated 150,000 badgers have been killed; according to DEFRA, last year’s count was 38,642. (The killing takes place despite the Protection of Badgers Act of 1992, introduced to combat badger-baiting and one of the country’s strongest wildlife protection laws, which is suspended to allow culling.)
“It’s an utter disgrace that we are still culling an iconic species of our native fauna for no scientific reason,” says Chris Cheeseman, a mammal ecologist, who worked as a scientific adviser on the Randomised Badger Control Trial. in his view, “there is nothing in the scientific literature that stands up to scrutiny that suggests culling works. It’s purely political.”
Iain McGill, a veterinary scientist who helped expose the government’s cover-up of Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease (“mad cow disease”) during the 1990s, agrees. “There is a lot of evidence that cattle give TB to badgers,” he says. “There’s precious little evidence that it goes the other way.” But DEFRA and the National Farmers Union “continuously” lead farmers “to believe that killing badgers will solve their problem.”
A spokesman for the National Farmers Union cites a report by the Animal and Plant Health Agency, which concluded that in high-risk areas in 2020, badgers accounted for 56.1 percent of TB infections in cattle—“further evidence that by controlling the badger population as part of a suite of policy measures, the number of new TB breakdowns can be minimized.”
“During the seven weeks of culling in 2019, a badger was being shot every 40 seconds,” Rosie Woodroffe, a biologist at the Zoological Society of London who has studied badger and cattle interactions, wrote in a March 2020 post for her blog. Since then, she says, the cull zones in England have gotten bigger, covering an area greater than Israel. “I think this is an embarrassment for a government that claims to show global leadership in protecting wildlife,” she says. “But there is a huge investment in this cull, and a huge conviction in the farming community that it is working.”
Defending badgers
“To see badgers foraging peacefully towards the end of a cull is a huge relief,” says the activist as we watch my first badger snuffling up worms. “But,” she adds, “when the numbers come out next year, it will be a punch in the stomach. There’ll probably be 60,000 or 70,000 killed, including 8,000 to 10,000 here in Somerset. It’s a massacre.”
A retired television producer, she has a soft-spoken, motherly quality, which belies a steely determination to oppose badger culls. This year, she estimates, she’s put in nights of patrolling equivalent to four working weeks. “I have had a lifelong interest in conservation,” she says, “which probably goes back to reading Gerald Durrell’s book My Family and Other Animals as a child.”
Our night had begun in a field below a nature reserve a few miles from where we saw the badger. “Unfortunately, the government has allowed cull operatives to set traps and shoot badgers on the borders” of reserves like this, she says. “They stick holes in the ground and put peanuts in to attract the badgers and keep them static so they can take a clear shot.”
This is known as free shooting, and it’s done by licensed operators from commercial culling companies, most led by farmers. One night last year, she and several colleagues confronted two shooters in the same field in a four-by-four. They had a high-powered rifle with a thermal-imaging scope and were firing uphill toward the reserve.
“The problem is if they hit the badger but don’t kill it, and the badger runs back to the sett, they can’t take a follow-up shot because they don’t have permission to follow it into the adjoining woodland, she says. “That would be a criminal offense.”
Things quickly turned ugly, she says. “It became a bit aggressive, with people arriving in cars and yelling abuse at us.”
“The police visited the cull company and discouraged the shooters from trying to kill badgers near the reserve,” she says. “So that was a win-win situation. And the badgers are still here.”
According to Ranald Munro, a retired professor of forensic veterinary pathology who in 2013 chaired an independent panel on the efficacy and humaneness of culling, the government is fully aware that free shooting entails serious animal welfare problems. “This was the best investigation of shooting injuries ever undertaken,” he says in a phone call from his home in Scotland. “Our report showed that up to 9,000 badgers were getting injured or not being retrieved after shooting, which meant they were suffering for more than five minutes”—in other words, an unreasonably long time. “But the government came back and said, We don’t accept that result.”
‘Incredible animals’
James Small has sheep as well as cattle on his farm in the Mendip Hills, in north Somerset. “I’m third generation on the farm, but the family has been in the area since the 1500s,” he says as we head out across the fields in his four-by-four to look at his cows. He’s dressed in traditional British country gear: muddy Barbour jacket, blue overalls, and Wellington boots, with a black baseball cap emblazoned with the logo of Warren Farm pulled down low over his brow.
It’s a spectacular setting—a plateau stretching away under a big sky dotted with scudding clouds. Below us is famous Cheddar Gorge, a 400-feet-deep gash hemmed by soaring rocky cliffs and pinnacles where badgers have lived for some 60,000 years. “There’s not much between us and the Appalachians, so the winds do tend to blow up here,” Small says with a laugh.
Badgers “are incredible animals,” he says. “They have very strong social groups, with complex hierarchies.” Despite his regard for badgers, he’s as adamant that culls are needed as activists are that they aren’t. “No one wants to be doing the wildlife controls, but at the moment, it’s the best thing we have,” he says. Since badger culls began in Somerset in 2013, bovine TB rates in the county have fallen by 50 percent, proof for DEFRA that culling works.
As we descend a field on the north side of the gorge, we find a herd of about 40 Irish blue-grey cows and calves milling about by a gate. Because of bovine TB, Small’s herd is subject to a stringent testing regime. "You have the logistical problems of getting the animals in [for] the testing with the vet,” Small says. “Then you have a four-day wait. We could go clear, or we could lose the whole lot. Even if it’s just one or two, your whole herd goes into lockdown.” Lockdown means no cattle can be sold or transported. Any animal that tests positive is slaughtered under the direction of the government’s Animal and Plant Health Agency.
Small says he’s lost 25 of his animals to the disease in recent years. “You can have generations of breeding, hundreds of thousand pounds of investment, taken away in the back of a lorry,” he says. “You can’t really quantify the emotional distress.”
Alternatives to culling
Every year, the government spends more than $130 million on the culls, and the cost of policing them comes to nearly four million dollars.
A report by DEFRA in September showed that the incidence of bovine TB in England and Wales had decreased by just 0.3 percent during the previous 12 months. Meanwhile, from June 1, 2020, through June 30, 2021, more than 41,000 TB-infected cattle were slaughtered, an increase of 7 percent over the previous year. “At the moment, the 100 million pounds the government is spending is just to manage the status quo,” says McGill, the veterinary scientist. “All we are doing is carrying on a well-worn track that is not effective.”
DEFRA seems to have come to the same conclusion. In May 2021 it officially announced plans to phase out badger culls over several years and replace them with a vaccination program. “The last possible year of intensive and supplementary badger culls will be in 2025,” when the cattle vaccine is expected to be ready for widespread use, a DEFRA spokesperson confirmed in an email. The announcement came with a big caveat: “We don’t want to continue culling badgers forever,” says Middlemiss, the U.K.’s chief veterinary officer. “But I am keen that we retain culling as a tool in the box where a hot spot area occurs, and we identify that badgers are involved.”
The decision to wind down regular culling was immediately condemned by the National Farmers Union as “incredibly disappointing and frustrating.”
Biologist Rosie Woodroffe says she’s cautiously optimistic. “You can’t cull to the point of eradication. Whereas with vaccination and better cattle movement controls, you could get to the point where the disease actually disappears,” she says.
James Wood says more accurate bovine TB tests are needed too because millions of cattle are moved around the country each year. “Cattle are the most important vector of this disease,” he says. “That’s why I am pushing for the use of much more sensitive tests to try and stop cattle transmitting the infection.”
The current test involves injecting a small amount of tuberculin in a cow’s neck and monitoring the size of the lump that appears. The test has a success rate of between 50 and 70 percent, so when a herd is declared tuberculosis-free, many animals remain infected and can spread the disease.
“As we’ve seen with COVID, the things that are crucial are a proper test, vaccination, and movement controls, none of which are in place for TB,” McGill says.
Meanwhile, some 140,000 animals may be killed before the ban goes into effect, and so the badger defenders will keep up their vigils. “People come from all over the U.K. and even from Europe,” says one cull saboteur, or “sabber,” in Shropshire, a predominantly rural county on the border with Wales. “We have people of all ages and from all walks of life. We had one 81-year-old pensioner who sat by a sett every night with a folding chair and a thermos of tea.” He paused. “It’s been a very good campaign this year,” he says proudly. “We have saved lots of badgers.”]]></text>
</doc>
